Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, Daf Chet דף ח, Daf Chet,
and we pick up with the Gemara גמרא Gemara right after the
Mishnah משנה Mishnah on Zayin Amud Bet ז עמוד ב. Zayin Amud
Bet. We had just read the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. Welcome back, Charlie.
We had just read the Mishnah משנה Mishnah that's now going to
do the question of who is considered the owner of the korban
קרבן korban to do temurah תמורה. temurah. So a normal person sanctifies
the korban קרבן, korban, brings it to the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Although the Kohen כהן Kohen will eat from the meat,
if it's a chatat חטאת chatat or an asham אשם, asham, it's
not his korban קרבן, korban, it's the owner's korban קרבן. korban. It's
the person who it's being mechaper מכפר mechaper for. So the Kohen
כהן Kohen cannot do temurah תמורה, temurah, only the owner. Kohen כהן
Kohen brings his own korban קרבן, korban, of course he's the owner.
And the focus of the Mishnah משנה Mishnah was about a bechor
בכור. bechor. And you had the interesting position of Rabbi Akiva רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, although resisted by Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri רבי יוחנן
בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, but this seems to be the
stam סתם stam of the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, that the Kohen כהן
Kohen is not the owner of the bechor בכור. bechor. The Yisrael
ישראל Yisrael had the bechor בכור, bechor, gave it to the Kohen
כהן. Kohen. The Kohen כהן Kohen treats it as a gift, as
it were, like he would receive the gift of the chatat חטאת
chatat of the meat of the chatat חטאת chatat and the asham
אשם, asham, but he is not considered the ba'al hakorban בעל הקרבן
ba'al hakorban and the Kohen כהן Kohen cannot do temurah תמורה. temurah.
Presumably the Yisrael ישראל Yisrael can do temurah תמורה temurah before he
gives it to the Kohen כהן Kohen and after that nobody can
do temurah תמורה. temurah. So let's take a look at the Gemara
גמרא Gemara because now the Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to focus
on exactly this question of the Kohen's כהן Kohen relationship to the
bechor בכור bechor that he is given while the animal is still
alive and he is going to actually bring this live animal as
a korban קרבן, korban, but nevertheless, according to our Mishnah משנה, Mishnah,
he does not really seem to be so much considered the ba'al
hakorban בעל הקרבן. ba'al hakorban. Yes.
I just as I was reading the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, I was
wondering, a bechor בכור bechor is very different from every other korban
קרבן korban in that it doesn't get sanctified, it is sanctified automatically.
Right.
So that's a very good point. So you might have actually thought
that nobody can do temurah תמורה temurah because maybe only the person
that instills the sanctity can do temurah תמורה. temurah. If you note
the Mishnah משנה Mishnah at the end spoke about that the kedushah
קדושה kedushah took effect, it says chalah alav חלה עליו chalah alav
in the owner's house. So although there was no instilling of kedushah
קדושה kedushah because that's when it became kadosh קדוש kadosh and the
owner is the one that is considered to be in the position
to do temurah תמורה. temurah. But you are correct that it is
unusual and you could have imagined that nobody can do temurah תמורה,
temurah, but we don't say that. You don't have to have been
the one to instill. Now I want to remind everybody that the
Gemara גמרא Gemara before set a position that if one person instills
kedushah קדושה kedushah and for it to be a korban קרבן korban
for somebody else, I sanctify my sheep to be an olah עולה
olah for Charlie or a chatat חטאת chatat for Charlie and now
Charlie is going to bring it, that actually Charlie does the temurah
תמורה temurah and I do not do the temurah תמורה. temurah. That
it is not a question of who instilled the kedushah קדושה, kedushah,
even in case when its kedushah קדושה kedushah was instilled, that does
not make me the ba'al hakorban בעל הקרבן. ba'al hakorban. The ba'al
hakorban בעל הקרבן ba'al hakorban is the one for whom it is
working for, who is bringing it, whom it is working for. But
given that, you would think that the Yisrael ישראל, Yisrael, the bechor
בכור bechor is never working for the Yisrael ישראל, Yisrael, it's sort
of being brought by the Kohen כהן. Kohen. And again, we do
have the point, so it's an excellent point that he's not instilled
the kedushah קדושה kedushah and then we also have this other point
that the Kohen כהן Kohen is not considered the ba'al hakorban בעל
הקרבן, ba'al hakorban, at least according to the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri seems
to disagree. So let's take a look now at the Gemara גמרא.
Gemara. Tnan hatam תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we taught over there in
Ma'aser Sheni מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, a bechor בכור bechor mochin oto
tam מוכרין אותו תם, mochin oto tam, we quote this Mishnah משנה
Mishnah a lot. Bechor mochin oto tam בכור מוכרין אותו תם Bechor
mochin oto tam chai uva'al mum חי ובעל מום, chai uva'al mum,
sorry, not this Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, a similar Mishnah משנה Mishnah which
we'll get to, excuse me. But anyway, here's the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah.
Tnan, bechor mochin oto tam
chai uva'al mum chai veshachut תנן בכור מוכרין אותו תם חי ובעל
מום חי ושחוט. Tnan bechor mochin oto tam chai uva'al mum chai
veshachut. You can sell a bechor בכור. bechor. Remember the pasuk פסוק
pasuk says by a bechor בכור bechor lo yipadeh לא יפדה, lo
yipadeh, it cannot be redeemed. By ma'aser מעשר ma'aser it says lo
yiga'el לא יגאל, lo yiga'el, that you cannot be, and lo yiga'el
לא יגאל lo yiga'el is learned out from the other pasuk פסוק
pasuk of lo yiga'el לא יגאל lo yiga'el where it says by
cherem חרם, cherem, where it's so by ma'aser מעשר ma'aser cannot be
sold or redeemed. Bechor בכור, bechor, the only prohibition is to redeem
it. It has this intrinsic sanctity as was pointed out, it wasn't
instilled. Because it wasn't a sanctity that was instilled, it cannot be
a sanctity that can be removed. So bechor בכור bechor cannot be
redeemed, but it could be sold. So you can sell it when
it's alive if it is unblemished. And if it is blemished, you
can sell it alive or dead. So what's the only thing you
can't sell it when it is
unblemished and
dead? Because what does it mean unblemished dead? Not dead, slaughtered. Means
it was unblemished, you brought it as a korban קרבן, korban, you
slaughtered it in the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Now once
you have meat of a korban קרבן, korban, you cannot engage in
commerce with meat of a korban קרבן. korban. But the meat of
a korban קרבן korban should be eaten by the owners or by
the Kohen כהן. Kohen. A bechor בכור bechor is eaten by the
Kohen כהן. Kohen. It is disrespectful for the basar hakodashim בשר הקדשים
basar hakodashim to be, you know, just sold like meat to someone
else. So once it's slaughtered as a korban קרבן, korban, you can't
sell it. But if it's alive, now the Yisrael ישראל Yisrael can't
sell it, he has to give it to a Kohen כהן. Kohen.
But he gives it to a Kohen כהן Kohen and the Kohen
כהן Kohen says, "Who wants to schlep שלעפ schlep this to the
Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש?" Beit HaMikdash? So anyway, so he sells it
to somebody else, another Kohen כהן Kohen who's bringing it to the
Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and that Kohen כהן Kohen will
eat it, will bring it. Okay, discount, you'll get some nice steaks,
you're going to the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he sells
it to him.
So there the כהן Kohen can sell it to somebody else, can
sell it to ישראל, Yisrael, can sell it to anybody he wants,
whether while it's alive or even after it's dead. So that's the
law of a בכור Bechor basically can be sold with the one
exception of after it's slaughtered.
Alive and no מום, mum, you can only sell it to a
כהן? Kohen?
Yes, because the הלכה halacha is a בכור Bechor is only eaten
by כהנים. Kohanim. Okay? It is not eaten, it's sort of like
תרומה Terumah in that respect. It's not קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, it's
not eaten only by male כהנים Kohanim in the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, it's קדשים קלים, Kodashim Kalim, but it's only eaten by כהנים.
Kohanim.
Okay, what so to the wife of a כהן Kohen or to
the slave of a כהן? Kohen? They have the same yes, yes,
yes. Okay, so that is a בכור Bechor as a קרבן. Korban.
A בכור Bechor as a with a מום mum can be eaten
by anybody. Alright, so that's how you can sell it, ומקדשים בו
את האשה. umakdishim bo es ha'isha.
And a כהן Kohen can use it to marry a woman. Once
it's his money, right? So and since it's alive he can sell
it whether blemished or unblemished, he can say, הרי את מקודשת לי
בבכור זה. Harei at mekudeshes li be'bechor zeh. Okay, and there he
can give it as כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin.
Why would we need that?
Well, sometimes that is used, often the question of what a man
can use to marry a woman is a good test case for
whether it's considered to be his property or not. Now, once you
can sell it, it seems clear that it is his property, but
sometimes you can say that no, maybe what you do is you're
selling the rights to it, the טובת הנאה. tovas hana'ah. So saying
that you can use it to marry a woman is a real
indication that this is really you own this object and therefore you
can use it as an object to as money for קידושין kiddushin
because it's a thing that you fully own.
Yes. And when she's married to the כהן, Kohen, then she that's
true.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah bar Avuha, לא שנו אלא
בזמן הזה. lo shanu ela bizman hazeh.
This is only talking about nowadays.
This idea that he can sell it. Okay, and also presumably that
he can marry a woman, but really the sense of ownership is
already communicated by the fact that he can sell it. This is
only true nowadays.
דהואיל ואית ליה לכהן זכייה בגוויה. de'ho'il ve'is lei le'Kohen zechiyah begavei.
Since nowadays even an unblemished בכור Bechor is only going to be
eaten once it gets its blemish. Okay, and therefore
it's never going to be brought as a קרבן Korban nowadays. Even
without a blemish you're going to have to wait. And therefore that
fundamentally translates into a very practical ownership. You'll wait till it gets
the blemish, you'll eat it wherever you want with its blemish without
bringing it as a קרבן, Korban, so the כהן Kohen is really
considered the owner. אבל, aval, now it's very interesting, like look what's
written in parentheses, it translates the phrase דהואיל ואית ליה לכהן זכייה
בגוויה, de'ho'il ve'is lei le'Kohen zechiyah begavei, הואיל ויש לכהן שותפות בו.
ho'il ve'yesh le'Kohen shutafus bo. Again, that just is an interesting indication
about the nature of this text. It's a very it's not such
a stable text. I presumably somebody wrote this in the margin, this
translation of the Aramaic phrase into Hebrew, and it's got inserted into
our גמרא. Gemara. It's then a later editorialized was a mistake, was
a gloss and took out. Anyway, אבל בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, aval
bizman she'Beis Hamikdash kayam, when there is a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
כיון דתם להקרבה הוא דקאי, kivan de'tam le'hakravah hu de'kai,
since the כהן Kohen is going to have to bring the תם
tam as a קרבן, Korban, אין מוכרין אותו תמים חי. ein mochrin
oso tamim chai. You cannot sell it because you're not really considered
the owner of the קרבן. Korban. So this really seems to reflect
the position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in the משנה. Mishnah. Although
the כהן, Kohen, which the גמרא Gemara will eventually tie in, but
we're going to have a whole עמוד amud before it gets to
our משנה. Mishnah. Although the כהן Kohen brings the קרבן, Korban, he
is considered, the phrase the גמרא Gemara is going to use is
משולחן גבוה קא זכו. mishulchan gavo'ah ka zachu. The same way a
כהן Kohen gets the meat of a חטאת chatas and an אשם,
asham, and he's not like the owner of the חטאת chatas and
the אשם, asham, the ישראל Yisrael is, and he just eats that
meat because he's eating the ישראל's Yisrael קרבן, Korban, but it's not
that he's the owner. Even when the ישראל Yisrael gives him a
live sheep as a בכור, Bechor, he's not bringing it, he's not
the owner of the בכור. Bechor. He brings it to the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, he eats the meat, but he's eating it as
it were משולחן גבוה mishulchan gavo'ah off of God's table. He is
not considered the owner for this animal that is brought as a
קרבן. Korban. Okay, so that is what he says, that's when there
is a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and if it's therefore unblemished, you
can't sell it. It's not yours to sell. You can bring it
to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you can be reward, you can
have the opportunity to eat the meat, but it's not yours to
sell. It is yours nowadays even without a blemish because it's not
headed for the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Yes.
Where it's a blemish, is it a permanent?
Yes, מום קבוע. mum kavua. Yes. Exactly.
And he can מקדש אשה, mekadesh isha, right. Okay, so exactly. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're going to spend
the rest of today's דף daf trying to prove or disprove this
statement. What is the status of the relationship of a כהן Kohen
to a בכור, Bechor, an unblemished בכור Bechor in the time of
the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Is he the owner or not? So
let's take a look. It's a great discussion which you wish we
would have had in בכורות, Bechoros, right?
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says, just shows you, you can
sometimes some very critical details appear in places you wouldn't expect it.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, איתיביה רבא לרב
נחמן. eisiv Rava le'Rav Nachman. So רבא Rava asked רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, challenges this position.
Where were we? Okay, מוכרין אותו תמים חי. mochrin oso tamim chai.
The משנה Mishnah says that we quoted, you can sell it unblemished
alive. חי אין שחוט לא. chai in, shachut lo. So meaning meaning
that we can, it's contrasting it and saying you can't sell it
unblemished slaughtered once it's already brought as a קרבן. Korban. You can
only sell it when it's unblemished alive before it's actually been brought.
אימא, Eima, so what time period are we talking about? אילימא בזמן
הזה, Eilima bizman hazeh, if we're talking about nowadays, מי איכא תם
שחוט, mi ika tam shachut, then how do you don't have the
scenario of having a slaughtered unblemished animal? You can't do that, right?
Because you have to wait till it gets a blemish. אלא בזמן
שבית המקדש קיים. Ela bizman sheBeis HaMikdash kayam.
So if we are implicitly saying not when it's unblemished slaughtered, we
mean not when it's brought as a קרבן. Korban. So we're talking
in a time when you bring things as a קרבן. Korban. Talking
in the time of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ותני נמי, Vesani
nami, and in that context that we're assuming to be the time
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we're saying מוכרין אותו תמים חי,
mochrin oso tamim chai, you can sell it unblemished alive. So the
משנה Mishnah that says unblemished alive, which you tried to claim was
talking only when there's no בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, he's saying no,
it's implicit in that משנה Mishnah that we're talking when there is
a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, because the implicit point of that משנה
Mishnah is not after it's brought as a קרבן. Korban.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: לעולם, Le'olam, no, no, you
don't have to read the משנה Mishnah that way. לעולם בזמן הזה,
Le'olam bizman hazeh, it's talking about nowadays. So מי קתני מוכרין אותו
תמים חי אין שחוט לא? mi kasni mochrin oso tamim chai in,
shachut lo?
It's not, you know, like this is actually, you know, the גמרא
Gemara often tries to infer things, you know, and say, oh, the
implication is it's trying to tell me, you know, the following. No,
no, no, don't be, don't overread the משנה. Mishnah. It's not telling
you you can't sell it once it's slaughtered. We, we're not, that's
a non, that's a not relevant scenario. It's בזמן הזה. bizman hazeh.
But הא גופא קא משמע לן, ha gufa ka mashma lan, it
comes to tell us the very facts themselves. דבזמן הזה נמי מוכרין
אותו תמים חי, De-bizman hazeh nami mochrin oso tamim chai, that nowadays,
although there's, although you,
actually nowadays, maybe דוקא davka because it can't be brought as a
קרבן, Korban, now, therefore you're able to sell it unblemished alive. Okay,
it's not dealing with the scenario of unblemished slaughtered, not because that's
a possible scenario but you're not allowed to sell it. That's, it's
not dealing with that because that's not a possible scenario because we're
talking about nowadays. So we're not going to discuss the scenario of
having brought it as a קרבן. Korban. But within the scenarios that
are possible because we're talking about nowadays, you can sell it in
all those cases. Okay, so you cannot prove from that משנה Mishnah
that we're talking about the time of a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Okay, so now we're going to keep on going and try to
prove this. See cases where you can sell a בכור bechor and
try to bring evidence that they're talking about when there is a
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and to prove that a כהן Kohen is
considered the owner of a בכור bechor when there is a בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Let's take a look. איתיביה, Eisivei, דף ח' עמוד
א'. daf ches amud aleph. He asked him on this, okay, something
that we quoted earlier, ברייתא braisa we quoted earlier. ובבכור נאמר לא
תפדה. U-ve-vechor ne'emar lo sipadeh. By a בכור bechor it says it
cannot be redeemed. So the only restriction is to redeem it.
ונמכר הוא, Ve-nimkar hu, and but it can be sold. Okay, so
that's the same point that you're allowed to sell a בכור. bechor.
במאי עסקינן, Be-mai askinan, what's the case? אילימא בזמן הזה, Eilima bizman
hazeh, nowadays, and it's because then this כהן Kohen is considered the
owner. So אימא סיפא, eima seifa, look at the end of this
ברייתא. braisa. It says ואת דמם תזרוק על המזבח, ve-es damam tizrok
al ha-mizbe'ach, quotes the פסוק pasuk that you put the blood of
a בכור bechor on the altar.
So בזמן הזה מי איכא מזבח? bizman hazeh mi ika mizbe'ach?
So, I'm sorry, not the end of the ברייתא, braisa, the end
of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, thank you. So it says, right, we're
quoting a פסוק. pasuk. It says לא תפדה ואת דמם תזרוק על
המזבח. lo sipadeh ve-es damam tizrok al ha-mizbe'ach. So we're דרשנינג darshaning
the beginning of לא תפדה, lo sipadeh, don't redeem it but yes
sell it. So it said okay, but we're doing that from a
פסוק pasuk that the end of the פסוק pasuk talks about bringing
it as a קרבן. Korban. So clearly the beginning of the ברייתא
braisa is talking when it in theory could be brought as a
קרבן, Korban, when there's a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And it's still
saying don't redeem it but yes sell it. Okay,
so פשיטא, pshita, אלא פשיטא בזמן שבית המקדש קיים. ela pshita bizman
sheBeis HaMikdash kayam. So the פסוק pasuk clearly is talking when there
is a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It says sprinkle the blood on
the altar. ובמאי, U-ve-mai, now what, now what type of בכור bechor
are we talking about? אילימא בבעל מום, Eilima be-ba'al mum, if it's
a blemished one, אימא סיפא ואת דמם תזרוק על המזבח ואת חלבם
תקטיר. eima seifa ve-es damam tizrok al ha-mizbe'ach ve-es chelbam taktir. מי
חזי בעל מום להקרבה? Mi chazi ba'al mum le-hakravah? So the end
of the פסוק pasuk says that you're bringing it as a קרבן,
Korban, right? So obviously when do you bring something as a קרבן?
Korban? When there is a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and when it's
unblemished. So the פסוק pasuk is talking about
unblemished with a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And the beginning of the
פסוק pasuk says don't redeem it and the דרשה drasha is don't
redeem it but yes sell it. So now you see you can
sell an unblemished בכור bechor when there's a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
אלא לאו בתם, Ela lav be-tam, it must be an unblemished, וקתני
נמכר, ve-kasni nimkar, and the דרשה drasha is that you can sell
it. You can sell this animal that otherwise you would bring as
a קרבן. Korban. Oh. So the גמרא Gemara says מידי אירייא? midi
irya? What, is that a proof? רישא בבעל מום וסיפא בתם. Reisha
be-ba'al mum ve-seifa be-tam. The beginning of the פסוק pasuk is the
דרשה drasha is about a blemished animal and the end of the
פסוק pasuk the דרשה drasha is about an unblemished, okay, which actually
makes nice sense because the פסוק pasuk is saying don't redeem it.
What type of animal would you want to redeem? You'd want to
redeem an animal with a blemish. So the way we're reading the
פסוק pasuk is you have a בכור. bechor. If it's got a
blemish, don't think about redeeming it. Sell it, yes, but don't think
about redeeming it. And if it doesn't have a blemish, then bring
it as a קרבן. Korban. Okay, so that's how we're reading the
פסוק pasuk and therefore again you cannot prove that we are saying
you're allowed. to sell a בכור bechor. *bechor* when it's unblemished and
there is a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beis HaMikdash*.
Wait, wait, why do you not want to redeem it but want
to sell it?
You're allowed to sell, you're not allowed to redeem it. The nature
of a בכור bechor *bechor* is since the קדושה kedushah, *kedusha* wasn't
instilled, the קדושה kedushah, *kedusha* came naturally by virtue of its being
a בכור bechor. *bechor*, you cannot transfer the קדושה kedushah *kedusha* elsewhere.
So the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s reading the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
is, you've got a בכור bechor. *bechor*, so it says לא תפדה
*lo tipadeh*, even if it has a blemish don't redeem it because
you can't redeem, you're not able to halachically, you know, able to
redeem, parentheses, but you can sell it with a blemish, and then
the end of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* says, oh, but if it
doesn't have a blemish, then go ahead and bring it as a
קרבן korban, *korban*. Okay, so that's how we're reading the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*, but again, so we accept that with a blemish you can
sell it because since it's not a קרבן korban. *korban* now you
are considered to be the owner of it, you'll eat it wherever
you want, you the כהן kohen, *kohen*, but if it has a
blemish, if it doesn't have a blemish and it's in the time
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and he has to
bring it as a קרבן korban. *korban*, then he is just considered
to be as it were eating it off of God's table, he
is not considered to be the actual owner. So we are still
trying to kind of prove that this question, can you sell a
בכור bechor. *bechor*
when unblemished בכור bechor, *bechor* at the time of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*? Let's keep on going. מתיב רב משרשיא *Masiv
Rav Mesharshiya*, so רב משרשיא *Rav Mesharshiya* asks from the following ברייתא
*braita*, כהנת שנתערב ולדה בולד שפחתה *Kohenes shenisarbeh vlada bevlad shifchasah*. Okay,
so this is a fascinating case. If you remember when we learned
בכורות bechoros? *Bechoros* throughout בכורות bechoros *Bechoros*, a very common case was
you had a ספק safek בכור bechor *safek bechor*. You didn't know
if it was the firstborn or not. So what do you do?
You don't have to give it to the כהן kohen. *kohen*. He
can't prove that he's entitled to it. You keep it in your
house, you wait till there's a blemish and you eat it wherever
you want. Okay, now we're dealing with a case of the ספק
safek *safek* is not in the בכור bechor *bechor*, but the ספק
*safek* is in the person, that basically
a wife of a כהן kohen *kohen* gives birth to a child,
a little baby כהן kohen, *kohen*, but then there is a mix-up
in the hospital and she doesn't know
which is her baby and which is the baby of her slave
woman. Okay, so it's an עבד eved *eved*. So now you have
a person who they grow up and they know one of them
is a כהן kohen. *kohen*, the other of them is actually the
slave to the other, the עבד eved *eved* of the כהן kohen.
*kohen*, and they don't know who is who. Okay, so how are
they going to deal with this in the rest of their lives?
So we're going to get to the question of how they'll deal
with it if they have a בכור bechor, *bechor*, but now we're
going to before we get to that let's look at some scenarios.
So הגדילו התערובת *higdilu hata'aroves*, this mixture grew up, calling them a
mixture, these two men grew up, okay, what do they do? First
thing they do is משחררין זה את זה *meshachrerin zeh es zeh*.
They free one another. Each one writes a שטר *shtar* and says
if I'm the master and you're the slave, I'm freeing you, and
they each do that for one another. So now they're both free
men, except the one that was a freed slave isn't a כהן
kohen, *kohen*, he's just a ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*. Yes.
But isn't there Torah prohibition about freeing...
Yes, but that is overridden when or you know the question is
that's not an absolute prohibition, like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a
case where somebody freed his slave in order to make a מנין
*minyan* and other situations, right, so the basic point is that when
there's enough of a good motivation you're allowed to, okay, but we're
not going to fully analyze that now. He now, okay, ושניהם אוכלין
בתרומה *ushneihem ochlin bitrumah*. Now before they freed one another, they can
both eat תרומה terumah. *trumah*, because one of them is a כהן
kohen. *kohen* and the other is an עבד *eved* of a כהן
kohen *kohen*, so they can both eat תרומה *trumah* before they've freed
one another. Okay, וחולקין חלק אחד על הגורן *vecholkin chelek echad al
hagoren*. Even so, when they go to the threshing floor and they
ask for their תרומה *trumah*, they only get one portion, they don't
get two. There's a question whether a slave of a כהן kohen,
*kohen* can go to a threshing floor and demand his own portion
of תרומה *trumah*, because first of all he's only eating it by
virtue of his master the כהן kohen *kohen*, and also there's a
general question of whether you can give תרומה *trumah* to a slave
of a כהן kohen, *kohen* directly because people will then think he
is a כהן kohen, *kohen*. So what they and so if any
one of them went individually to ask for their תרומה *trumah*, the
person would say I you know I don't believe you're the כהן
kohen. *kohen*, I believe you're the slave of the כהן kohen *kohen*,
and I don't give directly to slaves of כהנים kohanim *kohanim*. Okay,
number you know because you know because I don't want them to
get confused with כהנים kohanim *kohanim* or you're not entitled to it
directly, you're only entitled to it by virtue of your master. So
they go together as a pair to the threshing floor and they
say one of us is a כהן kohen *kohen* and is entitled,
and therefore but they only get one portion
because... And then like a wife of the כהן kohen *kohen* can
she go and get... So yeah that's a good point, I would
assume so since the only problem by the עבד *eved* you know
I don't remember it being discussed but I'm sure it is somewhere,
the only problem by the עבד *eved* is that people will confuse
him for being a כהן kohen *kohen* himself, but by the wife
of the כהן kohen *kohen* they might be confused whether she's the
daughter or the wife but it's not the same right but it's
not the same concern, yeah I assume so. I mean again the
question...
Isn't it only because she gets it in virtue of somebody else
then she still shouldn't be getting it because...
No well then the question is like would he have to give
you know the next כהן kohen *kohen* you know that's a question
of like keeping track like if the husband then comes can he
say I already gave at the office you know I already gave
to your wife, is it his responsibility to keep track and so
on. So I don't know but the greater concern here is the
one of status. So it might very well be true. Okay now
that so that's in terms of... while they're mixed up. Now, בכורן
bechoran, again, they're still mixed up, they haven't freed one another. And
now there's a בכור. bechor Now, if I had a בכור bechor
and they came to me, I would say, first,
not only prove to me you're a כהן, kohen but I would
actually say, I don't have to give to you even if I
knew you were a כהן. kohen I get to choose which כהן
kohen. I'm giving it to. So there's very little relevance if the
ישראל Yisrael has a בכור. bechor He's not required to give to
either.
But the question is, let's say they have a בכור. bechor, One
of these guys has his own flock and has a בכור. bechor
Now, if he knew he was a כהן, kohen. what would he
do? He would keep it and bring it as a קרבן, korban
right? If it's unblemished, he'd have to bring it as his own
קרבן. korban. But he says, I don't know if I'm a כהן.
kohen, I might be an עבד of a כהן. kohen If I'm
the עבד of a כהן, kohen, I don't get to keep the
בכור, bechor? I have to give it to a כהן. kohen, So
what does he do now with this animal? Does he keep it
himself or does he give it to somebody else? Okay, so let's
take a look. Does he have to find another כהן kohen to
give it to? So what is he going to do? So בכורן,
ירעו עד שיסתאבו ויאכלו במומן. yiru ad sheyistavu veyochlu bemuman. You wait
till it gets a blemish and then you eat it with the
blemish. Now, why? Because once it gets a blemish, you don't have
to bring it as a קרבן. korban, So what's the הלכה halacha
now? Once it gets a blemish, you're entitled to eat it wherever
you want, but the it might belong to a כהן, kohen not
belong to you. But then we go into just our normal דיני
ממונות dinei mamonot principle. What's our normal דיני ממונות dinei mamonot principle?
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. If it's just a
question of pure ownership, then it's you prove to me that it's
yours. So once it has a blemish, it becomes a pure question
of ownership and therefore since the other guy can't prove it's his,
I get to eat it. But without the blemish, it's not just
ownership, right? Without the blemish, there's the question about like who is
entitled to bring it as a קרבן korban. to the בית המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash And only a כהן kohen is entitled to bring it
as a קרבן. korban, I can't show up with this to the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because if I'm not a כהן, kohen I'm
not entitled to bring it. So in that therefore, we therefore you
have to wait till it has a blemish because you can't sort
of solve the problem without a blemish. I mean, so I guess
you could in that you could give it to another כהן, kohen
but you presumably don't want to give it to another כהן. kohen.
So that's what you do, you wait till it gets a blemish.
So the so no other כהן kohen. can say, listen, I know
I'm a כהן kohen, and you may not.
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to, that's why the
גמרא Gemara is bringing this in. Because why can't another כהן kohen
say this? Why can't another כהן kohen say, hey, you're not entitled
to wait till it gets a blemish, this has to be brought
as a קרבן, korban
I'm going to bring it, you know? And why doesn't the בית
דין Beis Din force another כהן kohen. to bring it? And the
fact that we don't is what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say proves that you really are the owner. So you can hold
on to it till a more advantageous time. But if the כהן
kohen were not really considered the owner, then the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash would force somebody to be bringing this. Okay, so let's take
a look. That's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
Okay, now, במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, what are we talking about? אילימא
בזמן הזה, ilima bizman hazeh, if it's nowadays, then מאי שנא דידן
ומאי שנא דידהו? mai shna didan u'mai shna didehu? What difference does
it make whether it is the בכור bechor of this weird ספק
כהן, safek kohen, or whether it does what difference would it make
if it was a בכור bechor. that a normal ישראל Yisrael had?
What's the הלכה halacha nowadays by בכורות? bechoros What do you do
with בכורות bechoros nowadays? You wait till they get a blemish. So
דידן נמי מומא בעינן, didan nami muma beinan, we also would require
a blemish. So the very fact that it sounds like, ah, because
of this problem, now we have to wait till there's a blemish.
It sounds like we're talking that there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and without this problem you would have brought it as a קרבן.
korban Because if it was nowadays, we always wait for there a
blemish. So אלא לאו בזמן בית המקדש קאי, ela lav bizman Beis
HaMikdash kai, we're talking that there was a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and there was an alternative, you could have brought it as a
קרבן, korban. but because we don't know who the כהן kohen is,
you have to wait for there to be a blemish. Now, let's
understand. ואי אמרת בשלמא אית להו לכהנים זכייה בגוויה, ve'i amrat bishlama
is lehu le'kohanim zchiya begavei, so now this is going if you
say that a כהן kohen is considered the owner of his בכור,
bechor. so therefore שפיר, shapir, now we understand, hey, I might be
the owner
and I can't bring it because I might not, but in case
I am the owner, I'm not going to let somebody else bring
it and I'm going to hold on to it until I can
eat from it, means until there's a blemish. Then the whole thing
makes sense. We'll allow you to hold on to it till there's
a blemish. אלא אי אמרת לית ליה, ela i amrat leis lei,
but if even for my own בכור bechor, I'm not really considered
the owner, okay, so then what happens? I've got a בכור bechor,
in my possession. It
can be brought as a קרבן korban. because it's unblemished. I don't
want to because I don't know if I'll be able to eat
from it. But who cares what you want? It's a בכור bechor,
that can be brought as a קרבן korban and if you're not
the owner, we the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash are going to ensure
that it's brought as a קרבן. korban, ליתי גזבר, leisi gizbar, let
the treasurer of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash come ולישקליה, u'lishkalei, and
take it. So, okay, normally you have
the opportunity to bring it yourself. But if here you can't bring
it yourself, we'll take care of it because at the end of
the day you're not the owner. So the fact that we don't,
that we let you hold on to it till it's more advantageous,
proves that you are considered the owner. So that's a very nice
proof. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. לא, לעולם בזמן
הזה, lo, le'olam bizman hazeh, no, we are talking about nowadays, that
there is no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and therefore you are the
owner. So if we're talking about nowadays, why what makes this special?
Everybody has to wait for there to be a blemish. So ודקא
קשיא לך מאי שנא דידן ומאי שנא דידהו, ve'deka kashya lach mai
shna didan u'mai shna didehu, how is ours different than theirs? Everybody
waits for a blemish nowadays. You're right, everybody waits. Wait for a
blemish. The חידוש chiddush wasn't wait for a blemish. Wait for a
blemish is taken for granted. Nowadays everybody waits for a blemish. What's
the חידוש? chiddush? Here's the point. אנן יהבינן ליה לכהן במומיהו. anan
yahavinan leh l'kohen b'mumeihu. We nowadays if it was a normal case
would whether there was or wasn't a blemish we'd give it to
the כהן. kohen, Okay, we have to give it to somebody else.
Yes, everybody waits for a blemish, but you give it to a
כהן. kohen But in this case, אינהו inhu this case of not
knowing who is the כהן, kohen כיון דאיכא במקצת כהן keivan d'ika
b'miktzas kohen since there's a partial כהן kohen meaning one of them
each guy might be the כהן, kohen מפקא ליה לכל הני mapka
leh l'chol hanei so therefore they get to hold on to it.
So basically what it's saying is, you're right, the חידוש chiddush here
although it's funny because that's not such a חידוש chiddush meaning what
it's really saying is, alright, we're talking about nowadays everybody always waits
for a מום. mum. And therefore all it's really saying is since
you're going to wait for a מום mum and since you might
be the כהן, kohen, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya
you don't have to give it to the other guy. But there
was no חידוש chiddush in waiting for a מום mum everybody would
do that anyway. The only חידוש chiddush is since each one might
be the כהן kohen he doesn't have to give it to the
other guy. So but you understand why the גמרא Gemara didn't like
that idea because the other way that's like a pretty obvious point
that we say all the time about like you know ספק by
בכור, bechor proof to me it's yours and normally it's proof to
me this is the בכור bechor... here proof to me you're the
כהן kohen and I'm not. But either way it's just a simple
monetary המוציא מחברו. hamotzi mechavero. It's a much bigger חידוש chiddush to
have said it the other way, to have said like because I
might not be the כהן kohen I can't bring it now as
a קרבן. korban. I am an אבן דכהן. even d'kohen. Since I
might not be the כהן kohen himself I can't bring it to
the קרבן korban. and I have to wait till it gets a
blemish. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to say we're talking that
there is a potential of a קרבן, korban there is a בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and therefore תוספות Tosafos says no, everybody's waiting for
a blemish, that's taken for granted, the only חידוש chiddush is you
have to you're allowed to keep it because המוציא מחברו. hamotzi mechavero.
Okay, לשון אחר lashon acher
and again as I mentioned a few days ago we're going to
have a lot of you know actually it makes the דף daf
go a little faster because takes up a couple space and it's
a good חזרה chazarah also, repeats the same idea in slightly different
words. לשון אחר, lashon acher, בזמן הזה bazman hazeh מאי יורייא בכורות
דהלן ספיקות? mai yorya bechoros d'halan sefeikos?
Nowadays and you'll notice also here really the different grammar stands out.
Nowadays if it's in nowadays so why is it what's special about
those cases of בכור? bechor אפילו דידן נמי יורייא afillu didan nami
yorya even normal בכורות Bechoros, everything you wait for a blemish. So
the fact that it sounds like this is special you wait for
a blemish, אלא פשיטא בזמן שבית המקדש קיים. ela peshita bazman she'Beis
HaMikdash kayam. There is a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you see
and also what are we talking about? We're talking about that it's
unblemished ואפילו במום v'afillu b'mum if it has a blemish already יורייא
yorya what does it mean let it graze until it gets עד
שיסתאב ad sheyista'ev let it graze until it gets a מום. mum.
המוסרבין בכהנים hamusravin b'kohanim they already have a מום. mum. אלא פשיטא
בתמי ela peshita b'tami so it must be that it's talking about
unblemished. So it's the same point. Since it says there's it reads
this that the חידוש chiddush is you wait for a blemish, it
sounds like we're talking about an unblemished animal clearly that in that
could have been brought as a קרבן. korban, And the חידוש chiddush
is you have to wait. So you see that that when there's
a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash unblemished and even so the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash. can't come in and grab the קרבן. korban. You the
כהן kohen are entitled have your property rights and are entitled to
wait. So the גמרא Gemara says no, ודאי לעולם בזמן הזה vadai
l'olam bazman hazeh we're talking about nowadays and therefore that's why you
have your
right. מאי קשיא לך? mai kashya lach? אפילו דידן נמי יורייא afillu
didan nami yorya even all קרבנות korbanos all בכורות bechoros you have
to wait for a
מום. mum. So לא מצית מדחית ליה לכהן lo matzis madchis leh
l'kohen in a normal בכור bechor you can't push away the כהן.
Kohen You wait for there to be a blemish but you have
to give it to a כהן. Kohen דלאו
איכא ספק הוא d'lav ika safek hu there's no doubt you're non-כהן,
Kohen the other guy's a real כהן Kohen and in a normal
case yes you wait for a blemish but you have to give
it to the other guy. הני ספיקות hanei sefeikos in this case
where one of them might be the כהן Kohen we don't know
who is who, מדחו לכהן madchu l'kohen they can push off another
כהן. Kohen כל חד וחד kol chad v'chad אמר ליה לכהן amar
leh l'kohen each one of them will say to some other guy
who wants it דאנא כהן ואנא כהן d'ana kohen v'ana kohen each
will say hey I'm the כהן Kohen I'm not giving it to
you. Okay, so again a nice way of reframing it but the
point is there's no חידוש chiddush of waiting for a blemish. Okay,
everybody waits for a blemish. It's talking about בזמן הזה. bazman hazeh.
The only חידוש chiddush is is that because they're a ספק no
other כהן Kohen. is entitled to it, they are they can keep
it because
המוציא מחברו. hamotzi mechavero. But again the הוה אמינא hava amina the
גמרא Gemara or the way it tried to prove it was fascinating
and it really illustrates the idea of the position that a כהן
Kohen is not the owner of his own קרבן korban, of his
own בכור. bechor, It's like you are allowed to bring it but
you're not bringing your בכור. bechor It's not yours. The ישראל Yisrael
gave it to you, you are the one who gets to bring
it but it's not yours. And what's the evidence? Because if it
was yours the גמרא gemara says if this were the time of
a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. and for some reason you didn't want
to bring it you wanted to wait for it to be a
מום mum because you didn't know if you're a כהן, Kohen, we
would come and give it to some other כהן Kohen to bring
it. So that really is showing illustrates this strength of this position
that a כהן Kohen is not the owner of his own בכור,
bechor he's given the ability to bring it
to
the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. and
that's it. So these...
what
do you want to call it, תערובות Ta'aruvot people? Yes. So if
they had a בכור, bechor would they be able to... they'd be
able to do תמורה, temurah, right? Because...
well, כהן Kohen can't do תמורה temurah regardless,
but because it's his own בכור, bechor so he can...
no, that's what the משנה Mishna says, כהן Kohen can't... oh, oh,
your own בכור Bechor you're saying, because by virtue of it being
the בית בעלים. beis be'alim. Right.
Okay, that's true.
So your point is... so your point is I can do בכור...
Bechor I can do תמורה temurah because it's... you would be able
to do תמורה temurah by virtue of being the בעלים, be'alim, whether
you're ישראל Yisrael. or כהן, Kohen right. Okay. Ability to do תמורה,
temurah, I will remind you all, is not a good thing. Right,
no. If you don't have the ability to do תמורה, temurah, then
you... then you won't sin. If you're the person that has the
ability to do תמורה, temurah, besides that you now get an extra
animal that's קדוש, kadosh, you've also transgressed. But yes, correct. Okay, so
now let's take a
look. Okay, where are we? מיתיבי. Meseivi. I'll ask you. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer, בהמתה, behemtah, פרט לבהמת בכור. prat l'behemas bechor.
So this is this fascinating other case, which is about destroying all
of the property in an עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachas, in a city
that was idolatrous. So there's a general principle, שללה, shlalah, all of
its booty, all of its wealth, ולא שלל שמים, v'lo shlal shamayim,
not things that belong to heaven, which means if there are, let's
say, עולות olos or... in there, or חטאת chatas animals that are
sanctified, let's say there's ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, מזוזות, mezuzos, okay, those
types of things are excluded.
Go around and find out, which is... is this the animal for...
like... I guess... it would be a big procedure anyway to gather
all the stuff up and destroy it. Anyway, so the דרשה drasha
though is not only those, but even בהמתה, behemtah, even its animals,
an extra thing which is re-emphasizing it has to belong to the
city, not to God. We already learned it from שללה, shlalah, but
this extra point is saying פרט לבהמת בכור ומעשר שבה, prat l'behemas
bechor u'ma'aser shebah, to exclude בכור Bechor and מעשר. ma'aser. Why might
I think בכור Bechor. and מעשר ma'aser might be different? Well, because
first of all, they're like קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, okay, you know,
they're lighter sacrifices, so there's a general position that קדשים קלים kodshim
kalim are ממון בעלים, mamon be'alim, are owned by the owners. Number
one. Number two is is that again, these are things that when
they do get a blemish, you don't have to transfer the קדושה,
kedushah are eaten with their blemish by the owners, right? So these
are things that are much more considered the owner's than let's say
a normal קרבן, korban and therefore maybe you would have to destroy.
No, the extra פסוק pasuk, בהמתה behemtah tells you you do not.
Now, שללה, shlalah, and the... the דרשה drasha of שללה shlalah is
פרט לכסף מעשר שני שבה. prat l'kesef ma'aser sheni shebah. So its
booty, which excludes the money of מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, this is
assuming מעשר שני ma'aser sheni is ממון גבוה, mamon gavoah, is considered
to be like God's money and God's property and not the owner's
property. Okay, we're not going to pay attention to the מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni right now. במאי עסקינן, Bemai askinan, what's the case? אילימא
בזמן הזה, Ilima bizman hazeh, if we're talking about nowadays, מי איכא
עיר הנדחת? mi ika ir hanidachas? Nobody's making an עיר הנדחת ir
hanidachas nowadays. והתנן, Vehatnan, we learned in a משנה, Mishna, אין עושים
עיר הנדחת אלא בבית דין של שבעים ואחד. ein osim ir hanidachas
ela b'veis din shel shivim v'echad. You need a בית דין Beis
Din of seventy-one, which presumably you didn't have when there wasn't the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So clearly the scenario is that there's a
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, Okay, now let's understand.
אלא פשיטא בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, Ela peshita bizman sheBeis HaMikdash kayam,
it's a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, ובמאי, U'vemai, what's the case? אי
נימא בבעל מום, Ei nima b'ba'al mum,
if the animal has a blemish, היינו בהמתה, hainu behemtah, so actually
then why is it excluded altogether? If it has a blemish and
you as the owner are really entitled to eat it anyway, and
you could be טמא tamei when you eat it, you know, and
so on, so okay, it has קדושה, kedushah but practically it's completely
your property. It wouldn't have been excluded, the גמרא Gemara assumes. אלא
פשיטא בתם, Ela peshita b'tam, if it's being excluded, it must be
unblemished and it's being brought as a קרבן. korban, Now, so okay,
but now let's understand about whether you would or would not be
considered the owner. אי אמרת בשלמא אית ליה זכייה בגוויה, Ei amrat
bishlama is lei zechiyah b'gaveih, if the כהן Kohen is considered the
owner of his בכור, Bechor שפיר, shapir, now I understand why you
need a פסוק, pasuk because on the one hand you're the owner,
on the other hand it's brought as a קרבן, korban so is
it considered to be your property, the property of the city, or
the property of God? You need an extra פסוק pasuk, to say
it's God's, don't destroy it.
אלא אי אמרת לית ליה, Ela ei amrat leis lei, but if
the כהן Kohen is never the owner, a בכור bechor is always
just the temple's, the כהן Kohen is just the person that has
the right to bring it but there's no owner, so if that's
true, so I don't need an extra פסוק, pasuk it's obviously not
the city's, it's obviously God's.
למה לי מבהמתה תפיק ליה, Lama li m'behemtah tapik lei, why do
you have to learn it out from an extra word of בהמתה?
behemtah? משללה ולא שלל שמים, Mishlalah v'lo shlal shamayim, learn it out
from the general verse that tells you not things that belong to
heaven. So again, the irony is is that the fact that we're
excluding it, which might have indicated... It's more not the כהנים's Kohanim,
but the fact that we needed to exclude it, we needed an
extra פסוק pasuk to exclude it shows us there was a reason
we would have thought it belongs to the set. And that's only
if the כהן Kohen is considered to be the owner. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, ובעולם בבעל מום. u'ba'olam b'ba'al mum. We're talking
with a blemish. If it didn't have a blemish then you're right,
it was never the כהנים's Kohanim and we would not have needed
a פסוק, Pasuk. it would have an extra פסוק Pasuk, would have
been obvious that it was excluded. We're talking with a blemish and
even with a blemish and even though the כהן Kohen can eat
it wherever he wants, it still doesn't get destroyed as an עיר
הנדחת. ir ha'nidachat. Why? דקשיא לך, d'kashya lach,
you're bothered, היינו בהמתה hainu beheimtah that actually is the property of
the city, right? If it's if the blemish can be eaten anywhere.
No, it has limits, there are ways in which its קדושה kedushah
is expressed. מי שנאכל בתורת בהמתה, mi she'ne'echal b'torat beheimtah,
only things that are eaten like normal non-sanctified food,
things that are eaten like normal חולין, chullin, right? I'm looking for
the in the English word lay, but lay is not the right
word. Anyway, what I mean is like regular meat. Okay. יצאו בכור
ומעשר שאינן בכלל בהמתה. yatze'u bechor u'ma'aser she'einan b'chlal beheimtah. A בכור
bechor and מעשר, ma'aser, although with a blemish they can be eaten
anywhere and even by טמאים, tme'im, they're not treated like totally normal
meat. Their קדושה kedushah is expressed in some way. How is it
expressed? דתנן, d'tnan, כל פסולי המוקדשין נמכרין באיטליז ונשקלין בליטרא. kol psulei
ha'mukdashin nimkarin b'itliz v'nishkalin b'litra. All animals that have a blemish, you
are once you redeem them, you are allowed to sell them in
the butcher stalls, like in the marketplace, and weigh them out by
the pound because once they've been redeemed you can treat them as
complete חולין. chullin. Nevertheless, חוץ מן הבכור ומן המעשר, chutz min ha'bechor
u'min ha'ma'aser, except for בכור bechor, and מעשר ma'aser because those are
not redeemed. So remember you don't redeem בכור bechor and מעשר, ma'aser,
you eat it with the blemish. Since you don't redeem it and
you eat it שנתנו לבעלים, she'nasnu l'ba'alim, there הקדש hekdesh isn't going
to benefit by the money you're going to redeem it with, it
remains yours and it's not redeemed. And therefore you have to you
cannot treat it in a way, even if you're allowed to sell
it, you can't treat it like totally normal meat. You can't sell
it in the marketplace with all the butchers, you can't weigh it
out by the pound. If you're going to sell it, it has
to be a private affair, more of an estimate and so on.
So the point being that even when it has a blemish and
you're allowed to eat it, its קדושה Kedusha is still expressed in
certain ways and therefore it is not destroyed with the with the
עיר הנדחת ir ha'nidachat because it is not completely like normal meat.
Okay, it's not a normal בהמתה. beheimtah. Okay, so again we've tried
to prove from the fact that you needed to exclude it, that
proved that there was an element to which it was yours because
it needed to be excluded. And the answer is no, we're not
talking about unblemished, we're talking about blemished and the exclusion is not
because it's not yours, the exclusion is because it's not treated like
normal meat. Okay, מיתיבי. meitivei. We're going to try yet again. ומעלה
מעל בה'. u'ma'alah ma'al b'Hashem. If somebody does trespass against God, what's
the case here? The case is וכחש בעמיתו בפקדון או בתשומת יד
או בגזל או עשק את עמיתו. v'kichash b'amito b'pikadon o b'tsumat yad
o b'gazel o ashak et amito. That somebody basically has something that
belongs to his friend, he owes him money, he has an object
for safekeeping and he takes an oath and he denies it. That's
מעל מעל בה', ma'al ma'al b'Hashem, he trespassed against God because he
denied it through an oath. So then when he admits and so
on, so he brings a קרבן korban. and he gives back the
object and he pays an extra fifth. That's the case in the
תורה, Torah, the פסוק Pasuk. at the end of פרשת ויקרא. parshat
Vayikra. Now because it says לה', l'Hashem, a trespass against God, so
there's a דרשה drasha that reads this as not only telling you
that the oath was a trespass using God's name, but that we're
even talking about if the object to some degree had an element
in which the object was God's. What is the case? But it
says you deny your friend, so how can you deny your friend
his object and the object is also God's? So we're talking about
certain קרבנות korbanot which have קדושה to some degree are God's but
also are considered to be the the property of the owner. So
let's take a look.
Why can't you just say that every time you make a שבועה
shvuah it's a מעל מעל בה'?
ma'al ma'al b'Hashem? Yes, that's certainly פשט, pshat, but there is a
דרשה drasha that feels that the תורה Torah did have to spell
that out, there was a הלכה halacha point to spelling it out
and it's coming to include even things that have to do with...
You can also say the Torah is making a moral point, like
it did just yesterday.
I understand. Okay, anyway, לרבות קדשים קלים שהם ממון בעלים דברי רבי
יוסי הגלילי. l'rabot kodashim kalim she'hem mamon ba'alim divrei Rabbi Yose HaGlili.
So this is the classic position of רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose
HaGlili, that he says for lighter sacrifices, things that are eaten in
all of ירושלים Yerushalayim and they're eaten by their owners. So the
fact that you are allowed to eat it in all of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, although it has קדושה and so on and it can't be
taken out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it has to be eaten within two
days, but nevertheless you are still you're considered because you're going to
have rights to the meat of this animal even after it's brought
as a קרבן, korban it's you're considered the owner. So that's an
example for him where your friend gave you his קרבן Korban. to
watch for him, watch this שלמים, shlamim, and then when he came
and asked for it you took an oath and you denied it.
So you're denying your friend his property, but it still is something
that is לה', l'Hashem, it still belongs to God, it's a קרבן.
Korban. So that's his proof that you can have something that is
a קרבן Korban? and is also your friend's property. What is that?
That's קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. That's what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGlili says. ואחרים אומרים v'acherim omrim לרבות שלמים. l'rabot shlamim. Not all
קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, just שלמים. shlamim. Why is שלמים shlamim different?
Because let me
just...
Yeah, because since we said before, right, for example by מעשר *Maaser*,
remember מעשר *Maaser* you're not allowed to sell a מעשר *Maaser*. There's
a limit of לא ימכר *Lo Yimacher*. What? מעשר בהמה *Maaser Behemah*.
מעשר בהמה *Maaser Behemah*, right. And that, so therefore there are some
limits that exist by מעשר *Maaser*, so he doesn't want to extend
it to all קדשים קלים *Kodshim Kalim*, but the classic קדשים קלים
*Kodshim Kalim* of a שלמים *Shlamim*. That's בן עזאי *Ben Azzai*'s slight
variation. אבא יוסי בן דוסאי אומר לא אמר בן עזאי אלא בבכור
בלבד *Abba Yosi ben Dosai omer lo amar Ben Azzai ela be-bechor
bilvad*. He didn't say all שלמים *Shlamim*, he just said בכור bechor
*Bechor*. Now בכור bechor *Bechor*, what makes בכור bechor, *Bechor* special? So,
so, one minute, right. So רש"י *Rashi* points out that the reason
he would exclude normal שלמים *Shlamim* is because normal שלמים *Shlamim* you
have, you do a תנופה *Tenufah*, you bring, right, you wave it,
you do סמיכה *Smichah*, you bring the נסכים *Nesachim*, bring oil libations.
So all of those extra trappings emphasize, although in practice you can
eat the meat anywhere in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, but all those extra trappings
emphasize that they're less yours, they're more the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash,
*Beis HaMikdash*'s. And מעשר *Maaser* you have limits because
you're not allowed to sell. So the only thing that doesn't have
all the trappings and that you're allowed to sell is בכור bechor.
*Bechor*. So only בכור bechor *Bechor* will I consider to be ממון
בעלים *Mamon Ba'alim*, everything else you have too many limits or too
many trappings to be considered yours.
So in the case of a שלמים *Shlamim*, so if you swore
falsely about it, you wouldn't have to?
You wouldn't have to because it's not really the owner's, the friend's
property. Okay, so that's בן עזאי *Ben Azzai*, it's a very subset
of רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili*. Now we're going to hone
in obviously on the בכור bechor. *Bechor*. So let's take a look.
במאי עסקינן B'mai askinan? *B'mai askinan*? What are we talking about? אילימא
בזמן הזה bizman hazeh, *I-leima bizman hazeh*, nowadays, can't be talking about
nowadays about these cases of these קרבנות *Korbanos*. הדומי דשלמים קתני *Ha-du-mi
d'Shlamim katani*, right, we mentioned a שלמים *Shlamim*, we mentioned things that
presumably are in a context of being able to be brought as
a קרבן Korban. *Korban*, because a בכור bechor. *Bechor* you could talk
about nowadays, you can eat it with a blemish. But we're talking
about all these other קרבנות *Korbanos*, we're talking about the world of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. Not nowadays where a בכור
bechor *Bechor* you can't control and you have it regardless. אלא פשיטא
בזמן שבית המקדש קיים *Ela p'shita bizman she-Beis HaMikdash kayam*. We're talking
about in the world of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. ובמאי עסקינן
*U-b'mai askinan*? What are we talking about? אילימא בבעל מום Ilima b'baal
mum, *I-leima b'ba'al mum*, if it's got a blemish, הדומי דשלמים קתני
*ha-du-mi d'Shlamim katani*, presumably it's like the case of the שלמים *Shlamim*
where the חידוש *chiddush* of saying that שלמים *Shlamim* was ממון בעלים
*Mamon Ba'alim* was that even though you're bringing it as a קרבן
Korban, *Korban*, you're still consider, it's still considered yours because you're going
to eat it. So we're in a context of things that are
being brought as a קרבן Korban, *Korban*, in the בית המקדש *Beis
HaMikdash*, and they're unblemished. And that context בן עזאי *Ben Azzai* says
בכור *Bechor* is considered yours. And presumably רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose
HaGlili* admits to that, he's just, בן עזאי *Ben Azzai* is limiting
it to בכור *Bechor*. So you see that it's considered yours by
בכור *Bechor*. So אלא לאו בתם Ela lav b'tam? *ela lav b'tam*,
it's unblemished, ושמע מינה כהנים Kohanim זכיה בגוה *u-shma mina Kohanim zachya
b'gavah*, you see the כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim* do have rights, so even
with the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, even unblemished. גמרא Gemara *G'mara* says,
אמר אביי *amar Abaye*, לא *lo*, no. לעולם בתם ובבכור בחוץ לארץ
*L'olam b'tam u-be-bechor b'chutz la'aretz*, I'll admit to you that it's a
time of a בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, I'll admit to you that
it's unblemished, all of those you proved a point, but we're talking
outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*. Why does that make
anything different? דרבי שמעון היא *D'Rabbi Shimon hi*, it's רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon*. דאמר אם באו תמימים יקרבו *D'amar im ba'u tmimim yikravu*, רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says בדיעבד *bedi'eved* if you bring a תם Tam,
*tam* from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz. *chutz la'aretz*, you'll bring it in
the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. But לכתחילה lechatchila *l'chatchila*, and this is
bizarre, we pointed this out at the time we learned it, בכור
*Bechor* is linked to מעשר בהמה *Maaser Behemah*, and מעשר בהמה *Maaser
Behemah* is linked to מעשר דגן *Maaser Dagan*, right, and therefore those
are things that really are only supposed to be done in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*. When it happens in חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz *chutz la'aretz*, it's not that it doesn't have קדושה *kedusha*, but
you're supposed to wait till it gets a blemish. Okay, which is
quite fascinating because that's not something that's linked to the agriculture, but
in a certain way, the whole idea about giving מעשר *Maaser* and
giving בכור *Bechor* and all those things imagines like Jewish society in
Israel. And if it happens in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz. *chutz la'aretz*,
the best is wait for a blemish. So here he says, look,
until now the answer we've had to all these cases to get
when it proved that you were the owner was to say it's
a מום mum *mum*. Here you've proven to me a case where
it didn't have a blemish, but I now have another, another answer
in my back pocket. It's in חוץ לארץ chutz la-aretz. *chutz la'aretz*.
And since in חוץ לארץ chutz la-aretz *chutz la'aretz* the הלכה *halacha*
is you're supposed to wait for it to get a blemish, it's
like it's בזמן הזה bizman hazeh *bizman hazeh*. So we all admit
that בזמן הזה bizman hazeh. *bizman hazeh* the כהן Kohen *Kohen* is
the owner because it's not headed for the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*.
So even, even בזמן בית המקדש *bizman Beis HaMikdash* without a blemish,
if it's in חוץ לארץ chutz la-aretz. *chutz la'aretz*, it's also not
headed for the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, and therefore that solves the
problem. So now we have three ways of getting out of any
proof that the כהן Kohen *Kohen* is the owner of the בכור
*Bechor*. Either say it's got a מום mum *mum*, or say it's
בזמן הזה bizman hazeh, *bizman hazeh*, or say even if it's time
of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, if it's in חוץ לארץ *chutz
la'aretz*, it's not headed to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, and that's
the scenario. Okay. מיתיבי
*Meisvei*, says the גמרא Gemara *G'mara*, I'll ask you on this, אמר
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri *amar Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri*, now we finally get back to our משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri. *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri* said
to רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, who said that the כהן
Kohen *Kohen* does not do תמורה Temurah *tmurah* with the בכור *Bechor*,
מה לי אם אינו מימר בחטאת ואשם *mah li im eino meimeir
b'chatas v'asham*, I understand a כהן Kohen *Kohen* can't do תמורה Temurah
*tmurah*... by the חטאת Chatas and the אשם Asham שהרי אין זוכין
בהם בחייהם, she-harei ein zachin bahem b'chayeihem, he has no rights to
them when they are alive. He’s never considered the owner of the
קרבן. He’s only eating the meat of somebody else’s קרבן. But חומר
בבכור שזוכין בחייו? Chomer b'bechor she-zachin b'chayav? What do you do about
a בכור that he actually has rights to it in his when
the animal's alive and he is the owner of a קרבן? So
it sounds like רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri is
making a clear statement that the כהן Kohen is the owner of
a קרבן. That proves that the that proves that the כהן Kohen
is the owner. Now you could say maybe that's what רבי עקיבא
Rebbe Akiva was debating, but if you remember רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
answered back based on a פסוק. pasuk No, it's where the קדושה
took place, which seems like in principle רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva agrees
with him. So now the פשט Pshat of the משנה Mishna. sounds
like in principle people agree that the כהן Kohen is the owner
of the קרבן, at least רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rebbe Yochanan ben
Nuri's So isn't that a proof against your position? So the גמרא
Gemara says,
where were we? במאי עסקינן? What are you talking about? אילימא בבעל
מום, mum back to that point. If it's got a blemish, הא
דומיא דחטאת ואשם קאמר. ha dumya d'chatas v'asham ka'amar. We're comparing it
to things that a כהן Kohen. actually does bring as a eat
the meat is brought as a קרבן, like the חטאת and the
אשם. Asham. אלא לאו בתם? We're talking about it's unblemished and we're
talking about a בית המקדש. All that is clear from the context
of the משנה. Mishna וקתני זוכין בו בחייו. V'katani zachin bo b'chayav.
And at least רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri says
and presumably it's clear that רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva doesn't disagree in
principle that the owner that the כהן Kohen has rights to it,
he is the owner of it. And so אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina,
הכא נמי בבכור בחוץ לארץ. Hacha nami b'bechor b'chutz la'aretz. Okay, now
that we've come up with our new answer, we're going to use
that's going to be an easy answer to use because you can
prove to me תם, tam, you can prove to me בית המקדש,
but I can just say, oh, it's חוץ לארץ. And therefore that
was רבי יוחנן בן נורי's Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri question. Can you
do תמורה Temurah on a בכור in חוץ לארץ where you really
are the owner? And the answer is even there רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva says no. Okay. רבי שמעון היא דאמר אם באו תמימים יקרבו,
Rebbe Shimon hi d'amar im bau temimim yikreivu, that you bring it
from חוץ לארץ בדיעבד, Chutz La'aretz b'di'eved, but לכתחילה you're not. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, לימא כתנאי. Leima k'tannai. Let now
by the way I should just take a moment to pause and
say that while the that the simple understanding of the debate of
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri and רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva is exactly this point. That רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan
ben Nuri is insisting that a כהן Kohen is the owner of
his בכור and רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva's is saying the כהן Kohen
can't do תמורה Temurah. although he did quote a פסוק, but but
it seems you know one way to understand it at a deeper
level is that רבי עקיבא's Rebbe Akiva claim is that he's not
the owner of the בכור. But the גמרא Gemara does not want
to frame their debate that that way because the simple reader of
the משנה Mishna. is that they agree in principle that he's the
owner, רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva's has a פסוק. So the way it
deals with this is by saying that it's חוץ לארץ. Let's take
a look. לימא כתנאי. Leima k'tannai. Maybe it's a debate it's connected
to a debate of תנאים Tannaim and here we really will have
a what seems to be a reframing of the debate of the
משנה. Mishna בכור בבית בעלים עושים תמורה בבית כהן אין עושים תמורה.
Bechor b'veis baalim osim temurah b'veis kohen ein osim temurah.
You can do תמורה Temurah for a בכור in the owner's house
but not once it's given to the כהן. Kohen. Seems like רבי
עקיבא's Rebbe Akiva. position. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rebbe Shimon ben
Elazar omer, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rebbe Shimon ben Elazar says, כיון
שבא ליד כהן אין עושה תמורה. Keivan she-ba l'yad kohen ein oseh
temurah.
Once the כהן Kohen? got it nobody can do תמורה. Temurah. Well
that seems to be what we just said, right? Because it's only
in the owner's house. Once he doesn't have it obviously he can't
do תמורה Temurah? anymore. So isn't it the same point? So the
גמרא Gemara says, היינו תנא קמא? Hainu Tanna Kamma?
Isn't that exactly what we just said? So מהי לאו הכי קאמר?
Mai lav hachi ka'amar? This is how you have to read it.
בבית כהן הוא עושה תמורה ואין בעל עושה תמורה. B'veis kohen hu
oseh temurah v'ein baal oseh temurah. That that
meaning בבית כהן b'veis kohen should be כהן עושה תמורה ואין בעל
עושה תמורה. kohen oseh temurah v'ein baal oseh temurah. Meaning that you
read the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma what he says you only do
it in the owner's house means only that the that the owner
can only do it while he has it, but once he gives
it to the כהן, Kohen then the owner can't do it and
the כהן Kohen can. And comes along רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rebbe
Shimon ben Elazar and says no, once the כהן Kohen gets it
nobody can. So basically, okay, it's not so clear but we've reread
this משנה that they're basically it's the same debate of רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri and רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva, Why
can't nobody do it? Because the כהן Kohen. is like רבי עקיבא,
Rebbe Akiva. the כהן Kohen. is isn't able to do תמורה.
Temurah But then at least the בעל Baal should be able to.
No, because it's not in his control. So we've reread this debate
which is question why the גמרא Gemara is focusing on this debate
because it's the basically we've just reread it as the debate of
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbe Yochanan ben Nuri. and רבי עקיבא. Rebbe
Akiva We've read that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that the
it's like רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, that the
כהן Kohen can do it and the position of of רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rebbe Shimon ben Elazar is that no, it can only
be done by the owner. Fine. So it's a debate of it's
the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי יוחנן בן נורי.
Can the כהן Kohen, do תמורה? Temurah. So now the גמרא Gemara
says let's take a
look. אלמא אית ליה לכהן זכייה בגוויה. Alma is lei l'kohen zachiya
b'gaveih. So the position that says the כהן Kohen. can do תמורה
tmura, says that the כהן Kohen has rights to it. So you
see that the you see that the exact same debate that we
so you see that this is a debate of whether the כהן
Kohen is considered the owner because they're debating whether the כהן Kohen,
can do תמורה. tmura So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא. Lo
kashya. No. הא רבי יוחנן בן נורי הא רבי עקיבא. Ha Rebbe
Yochanan ben Nuri ha Rebbe Akiva. Which is pretty much what we
were saying. It says fine, it's the same debate of רבי יוחנן
בן נורי, or חוץ לארץ. And therefore that,
but if there really is
ארץ ישראל, Yisrael you know, with a
בית המקדש, no blemish, the claim is that the כהן Kohen, is
not the owner. Then we said that seems to be the debate
of רבי עקיבא and רבי יוחנן בן נורי, which is whether the
כהן Kohen can do תמורה, whether is whether the כהן Kohen. is
the owner. And we say, no, again, that's חוץ לארץ and therefore
he is the owner and the position that he can't do תמורה
is based on a פסוק of בית בעלים, beis ba'alim, but fundamentally
he is the owner, but that's because it's חוץ לארץ. So we
still are trying maintaining our trying to defend the position that when
it is a case of תם, tam. בית המקדש, ארץ ישראל, Yisrael
that the כהן Kohen. is not the owner. Okay, let's take a
look at now the גמרא basically moves on a little bit. אמר
רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, says רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, לא שנו
אלא כהן לכהן, lo shanu ela Kohen le-Kohen, אבל כהן לישראל אסור.
aval Kohen le-Yisrael assur. We've now moved on. That's tried to really
prove our case, managed to push it all off, fine. It's not
resolved, but that person defended his position, that רב נחמן Rav Nachman
defended his position that a כהן Kohen is not an owner of
a תם. tam But when a כהן Kohen can sell it, when
can he sell it? Either if you assume that in general even
by a תם tam he's the owner, or it has a blemish,
okay, or it's בזמן הזה, bizman hazeh, okay, but when a כהן
Kohen is entitled to sell it, he can only sell it to
another כהן. Kohen Okay, so now on a totally new topic. אבל
כהן לישראל אסור. Aval Kohen le-Yisrael assur. But the כהן Kohen is
not allowed to sell his בכור to a ישראל. Yisrael, מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? דילמא אזיל ישראל ושדי ביה מומא, Dilma
azil Yisrael ve-shadi bei muma, because ישראל Yisrael will now have this
בכור that's unblemished. So if he sold it unblemished, we would be
talking about בזמן הזה or against רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Okay, so
כהן Kohen is selling an unblemished בכור, but maybe it's בזמן הזה.
But now what will ישראל Yisrael do? He'll go and put a
מום in it, because what good is a בכור nowadays without a
blemish? So he'll go and he'll put a מום in it, which
is a transgression, וממטי לחכם, ve-mamti le-chacham,
and he has to bring it to a sage to get a
sage to rule that it's a legitimate blemish. ואומר לו, Ve-omer lo,
what is he going to say? How'd he get the blemish? Says,
בכור זה נתון לי כהן במומו. bechor zeh natun li Kohen be-mumo.
Oh, I got it from the כהן Kohen with the blemish. He
doesn't want to say that he got it and it developed the
blemish by itself, because then everybody is going to suspect him, oh
right, got the blemish itself. So therefore he says, oh, I got
it with the blemish. Okay, and therefore we don't want that to
happen, and therefore we therefore only sell it to a כהן. Kohen
How's it going to help if you only sell it to a
כהן? Because as you right remember might remember from בכורות, bechoros we
are always suspicious of כהנים, because כהנים are always getting בכורות bechoros
and wanting to put blemishes in them. So therefore when a כהן
wants to eat his בכור with a blemish, he has to bring
witnesses. Okay, but we don't want to give it to ישראל, Yisrael
so we're not that we've protected ourselves with the כהן case. But
we don't want you to give it to ישראל Yisrael's because then
he has an incentive to make the blemish himself. So the גמרא
says, how'd that case happen? ומי שרי חכם הכי? U-mi shari chacham
hachi? And the sage won't allow it, won't rule on it. ואמר
רב, Ve-amar Rav, אין רואין בכור לישראל אלא אם כן כהן עמו.
ein ro'in bechor le-Yisrael ela im ken Kohen immo. You won't rule
on a בכור that ישראל Yisrael has without the כהן being there.
Why? Because we're not because of the blemish concern, but we're concerned
that he's not that that it's that
he has an obligation to give it to a כהן. What is
the ישראל Yisrael doing with this בכור, right? It should belong to
a כהן. So he's claiming, oh, a כהן sold it to me,
I got it back from a כהן, whatever. Why do we you
know, so we're concerned that if we just פסקן pasken for ישראל
Yisraels those cases, there'll be an incentive to never give to lie
and never give their בכורות to כהנים and to just say that
they got it back from a כהן. Okay, so again the גמרא
really understands the psychology here. You're פרום frum enough that you are
not going to eat it without a blemish, okay, but you're not
so פרום frum that you're not going to steal it, or you're
not so פרום frum that you're not going to put the blemish
in. But you are פרום frum enough to wait to get a
פסק psak from the rabbi that it does that the blemish is
a good blemish. So we don't want to פסקן, pasken, anyway not
going to פסקן pasken for you if you're ישראל Yisrael unless you
come with the כהן and that כהן says, oh yeah, I gave
it back to him, I sold it to him or whatever. Okay,
so therefore therefore we're not going to rule for you anyway. And
if you do come with the כהן, then we're going to ask
the כהן, when did it have a blemish when you sold it
to him? So there's nothing to be afraid of, okay, because we're
going to wait for the כהן and we'll check with the כהן.
So the גמרא says, I'm sorry,
wait, so what's our question?
We said don't sell it to a ישראל Yisrael because it'll be
an incentive for him to put a blemish and blame it on
the כהן. And the answer is, he won't have that option. Since
because we're afraid anyway that ישראל Yisrael. will want to steal the
בכורות from the כהנים, not give it to them, we're not going
to rule for ישראל Yisrael unless the כהן is with the ישראל
Yisrael, who and testifies to the fact that he sold it to
ישראל. Yisrael? And then if the ישראל if there's a blemish, he'll
have to take the כהן with him anyway and we'll be able
to ask the כהן when it got the blemish. Okay, so אמר
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, היינו
טעמא דישראל אסור. hainu ta'ama de-Yisrael assur. Here's why we don't sell
it to ישראל, מפני שנראה ככהן המסייע בבית הגרנות. mipnei she-nir'eh ke-kohen
hamisaye'a be-veis hagronos. You might remember this idea, common idea that comes
up. The כהן helps out in the threshing floor. We don't allow
a כהן to come and volunteer his services when right before the
time of תרומה. Anything you need done here? I'll come help out
at the threshing floor because we're afraid that then you... you give
him the תרומה *Terumah*, there'll be an implicit sort of exchange of
services, and then you're not really giving the תרומה *Terumah* as a
gift, you're really sort of giving it as a type of as
a type of payment. So therefore, that is a type of a
concern. We don't want that to be done in fact, and we
don't even want it to feel like that. So therefore, we don't
want a כהן *Kohen* to sell to ישראל *Yisrael* because what's going
to happen? You give if I start selling you the ישראל *Yisrael*
the בכורות *Bechoros*, then that'll be an incentive for you to give
me the בכורות *Bechoros*, because you know that I'll turn around and
sell it back to you at a discount. Okay, so because we
so therefore we'd rather you not sell back to ישראל *Yisraels*. כהן
*Kohen* you're not concerned, the כהן *Kohen* will just keep the בכור
*Bechor* himself. We don't want you selling it to ישראל *Yisrael* because
then it becomes a whole little deal and you're going to be
the one that he's going to give the בכור *Bechor* in exchange
for you selling it back to him. Okay, so that's why we
don't want it. So מר *Mar* now we're going to have a
story about this. מר זוטרא איקלע לבי רב אשי *Mar Zutra ikla
l'bei Rav Ashi*. מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra* came to the house of
רב אשי *Rav Ashi*. אמרו ליה *Amru lei* they presumably the servants
of רב אשי *Rav Ashi* said to him, לטעום מר מידי *lita
mar midi*, would you like to have something to eat? So sure.
אייתו לקמיה בישרא *Aisu lekamei bisra*, they brought in front of him
a nice piece of meat. אמרו ליה *Amru lei* they said to
him, ליכול מר *leichol mar*, you should eat this meat, דמברי *d'mivri*,
it makes you healthy, משום דבכורא הוא *mishum d'bechora hu*, it comes
from the בכור *Bechor*, and there was a sense that meat from
the בכור *Bechor* made you healthy. So then he said to them,
the servants, מנלכו הא *minalchu ha*, where'd you get the meat of
a בכור *Bechor*? You're not כהנים *Kohanim*. So again, with a מום
*mum*, fine, but you're not כהנים *Kohanim*. אמרו ליה *Amru lei* they
said to him, דזבין לן פלוני כהן *d'zavin lan ploni Kohen*. Oh,
so and so the כהן *Kohen* sold us his בכור *Bechor*. Again,
with a blemish. Okay, אמר להו *amar lehu* he said to them,
לא סבירו לכו הא דאמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע מפני שנראה
ככהן המסייע בבית הגרנות *lo seviru lechu ha d'amar Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua mipnei shenireh k'Kohen hamisaye'ah be'veis hagranot*? Don't you don't you
hold of the position that you're not allowed to buy בכורות *Bechoros*
from כהנים *Kohanim*? So again, although we thought the whole part of
the whole discussion was the כהן *Kohen* selling his בכור *Bechor*, we
now said it can only be to other כהנים *Kohanim*. So you're
not allowed to because it looks like you've got some deal
going. אמרו ליה *Amru lei* they said to him, לא סבירא לן
*lo seviru lan*. No, we don't hold of that. דאנן מזבן קזבנינן
*d'anan mizban kazavninan*, because we pay for it. Meaning the problem is
don't let the כהן *Kohen* volunteer services, do do something free for
you, because then it looks like it's an exchange. I did that
nice thing, I'm going to give him my בכור *Bechor*. But here
we actually paid for the meat. So it doesn't look like there's
some type of inappropriate exchange going on.
אמר להו *amar lehu* he's asking this publicly though, I mean what?
Publicly, right? What? If it's נראה *nireh*, I mean, you know, it
has to be נראה *nireh*.
I mean, right, okay, that could be. Well, the question I'm not
sure נראה *nireh* means it's מראית עין *maris ayin*, it might just
mean that it's, you know, that it that it just might. Anyway,
אמר להו *amar lehu*, so he said to them, ולא סבירו לכו
הא דתנן *velo seviru lechu ha d'tnan*, what about the משנה *Mishnah*?
Again, it's a question who is he talking to? And I said
the servants, they might have to be serious תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim*,
I don't know who exactly it is, maybe it's the students of
רב אשי *Rav Ashi*. Anyway, he's having this הלכתי *halachic* discussion. He
says, okay, what?
Maybe רב אשי *Rav Ashi* had them work for free in his
house?
Right, okay. Anyway, okay, that's very nice that you think it's very
nice you think you paid for it and it gets you out
of it, but how about the משנה *Mishnah* that says, עד כמה
ישראל חייב לטפל בבכור *ad kamai Yisrael chayav letapel b'bechor*, how long
do you have to raise the בכור *Bechor* in your house? Because
you the כהן *Kohen* can say, you know, if you don't give
it to the בכור *Bechor* one day old to the כהן *Kohen*
because he can't use something that old, you have to invest in
it till it grows up a little bit till you can slaughter
it. So actually we put that responsibility on the ישראל *Yisrael*. You
have to raise it for a while before you give it to
the כהן *Kohen*. You have to, you know, endure take on under
take that financial responsibility. So for how long? בדקה שלשים יום *bedaka
sheloshim yom*, small animals, sheep and goats 30 days, ובגסה חמשים יום
*uv'gasa chamishim yom*, for calves 50 days. Now, fine, so that's your
financial responsibility. ואם אמר לו *ve'im amar lo*, if the כהן *Kohen*
comes to you and says, I'm going to do you a favor,
I'll take it off your hands, תנהו לי בתוך זמנו *tneihu li
betoch zemano*, you don't have to raise it for the whole 30
days, I'll take it off your hands now. So then, הרי זה
לא יתננו לו *harei zeh lo yitnenu lo*, don't give it to
him now. That is clearly, right, inappropriate, because basically he's doing you
a favor, he's freeing you from the financial responsibility, and in exchange,
you're giving him your בכור *Bechor*. Okay, so there there's a type
of a obviously inappropriate thing. He does you a favor, you got
a בכור *Bechor*. But he says, ah look, here you see that
you gave a כהן *Kohen* a בכור *Bechor*, which he's entitled to,
and nevertheless it was inappropriate. Now the obvious difference is, yeah, because
there there was no purchasing. There it was a free giving of
a בכור *Bechor* in exchange for some favor that the כהן *Kohen*
did. So that's going to be the answer. You even really wonder
what the question was. So let's take a look. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, דאמר הכי *d'amar hakei*, what's the reason? מפני שנראה ככהן
המסייע בבית הגרנות *mipnei shenireh k'Kohen hamisaye'ah be'veis hagranot*, because it looks
like, you know, helping out in order to get a מתנה *matanah*,
a מתנת כהונה *matnas kehunah*. I'll do you a favor, I'll take
it off your hands, then in exchange, not only in exchange, the
actual thing itself is that you give it to me, it's like
right there, right, the favor and the payment for the favor is
the very fact that I'm taking it off your hands right now.
So אמר להו *amar lehu*, so they said back to him, no,
התם מוכח מילתא הכא מזבן קזבנינן *hasam mocha milta hacha mizban kazavninan*.
There
it's obvious, there it's an exchange, I do you a favor, you
give me your בכור *Bechor*. But here it's a sale, you sold
me, what are we afraid about? Right, we paid good money for
it. לשון אחר *lashon acher*, another version of
it, אמר ליה *amar lei*... הכא,
here, קא יהיב דמי. ka yahiv demei. So what are you so
concerned about? We're paying for the meat. What's wrong? מאי אמרת? mai
amarta? So now finally we're going to say what's the concern, what
is your concern that there might be something inappropriate here? מוזיל כהן
גביה? mozil Kohen gabei?
Maybe you're afraid that the כהן is going to give us a
discount. That's the favor. Yes, we're paying for it, but maybe it's
inappropriate because maybe he'll give you a discount. Why will he give
you a discount? In exchange for what favor? By giving you a
discount, next time you'll give him your בכור. You know that you
give him the בכור and he sells it back to you at
a discount. So that's your concern, that we're going to get a
discount. So he says דסבר כהן, desavar Kohen, he feels דכי הוי
ליה בכור אחרינא יהיב ניהלי. d'chi havei lei bechor achrina yahiv nihali.
If I give him a discount now, he'll sell me, he'll give
me his next בכור. That's your concern, right? That it's inappropriate. Not
the purchase, but maybe even though there's a purchase, maybe it's at
a discounted rate and it's inappropriate. He says for that concern, he
says לא דמסיק אדעתיה, lo damasik adaiteih,
that's not or לא מסיק אדעתיה, lo masik adaiteih, whatever. That's not
going to occur to him or that's not an issue to be
concerned about. Why? Because בוצינא טב מקרא, butzina tav mikara,
which basically is a bird in the hand is worth two in
the bush. A small, a small
gourd now is worth a, is better than a big gourd later.
He's not going to give me a discount on the hope that
in some future time I'll give him the בכור. If he's selling
it, he's going to make as much money as he can make
right now and he's not, there's not a concern and even if
he might be hoping that or whatever, that's not enough to be
concerned about about inappropriate. So in the end of this long issue
about is a כהן an owner of a בכור in order to
sell it when it's a תם ובזמן בית המקדש, uvizman Beis HaMikdash,
we ended with a very practical discussion about בזמן הזה, it has
a מום or whatever, it's בזמן הזה, he's allowed to sell it.
But can he sell it only to a כהן or is he
allowed to sell it to a ישראל? Are you afraid of the
appearance or some type of inappropriate exchange?